Leah: Nearly 10 percent of children
and young people experience behavioural
or emotional problems growing up and
for most, these will resolve in time
but for others, it won’t, and they
will need more professional support.
Rhiannon: It can be difficult to know
when a child or young person is suffering
but significant changes in behaviour,
difficulties with sleep, withdrawal or
not wanting to do things they usually
like to do, will be a potential sign.
Leah: Children with long term medical
conditions are more likely to suffer from
emotional problems or disturbed behaviour.
They may start to rebel or
withdraw from social settings.
Rhiannon: They may be susceptible to
using other methods to control their
problems such as self-medicating.
Teenagers as they grow up, start to get
moody and worried about how they look,
what other people think of them and
this can affect the way they behave.
They may change their eating habits
even becoming anorexic or bulimic,
and indulge in risky behaviours.
Leah: Self-harm is more common in
teenage girls than in boys, but boys
and young men are at a higher risk of
suicide, however suicide rates are on
the increase with young women also.
Cutting can become habit forming and
many people who self-harm, take care
to hide any scars and self-harmers can
be unpredictable with their ‘tools’.
Rhiannon: When it comes to addiction,
young people will not often seek help
but will present with other problems such
as difficulties at school, inappropriate
sexual behaviour or signs of depression.
They may even start lying or
stealing to feed their drug habit.
Leah: Behavioural and conduct problems
may be related to other complaints,
such as ADHD, specific learning
difficulties, abuse, or social influences.
This can have a negative impact,
not only on the child or young
person but on the whole family.
Rhiannon: Eating disorders not only
affect the individual mentally, but
they also affect them physically and
in extreme cases can cause death.
Anorexia in girls, causes problems
with their periods stopping
and other health problems.
Bulimia and the excessive use of
laxatives can cause physical damage
and regular vomiting can dissolve
and erode the teeth over time.
Leah: Psychosis can be caused by substance
abuse or can be a signal of an underlying
physical illness such as a severe
infection, or a severe mental illness
like bipolar disorder or schizophrenia.
Children and young people are often not
aware that they have a problem, until
it becomes a problem and this is where
parents, carers, friends, family, teachers
and anyone who knows them well, should
be aware of changes in behaviour or mood.
Rhiannon: If they are starting to
behave differently or show distress
or mood swings it should be a warning
that something isn’t right, and it
might be time to talk to someone
about it before things go too far.